<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://lizargall.github.io/blog</id>
    <title>Liz Argall Blog</title>
    <updated>2025-05-11T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog"/>
    <subtitle>Liz Argall Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://lizargall.github.io/img/favicon.ico</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[It begins!]]></title>
        <id>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/welcome</id>
        <link href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/welcome"/>
        <updated>2025-05-11T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to my new technical writing blog. First, a big shout out to the following thought leaders who have encouraged more technical writers to share their knowledge and opinions.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to my new technical writing blog. First, a big shout out to the following thought leaders who have encouraged more technical writers to share their knowledge and opinions.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://passo.uno/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Fabrizio Ferri Benedetti</a>
<ul>
<li>Terrific human whose blog posts stir conversations and help us build a better vocabulary for what we do.</li>
<li><a href="https://passo.uno/tech-writing-depth-issue/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Technical writing has a depth issue</a> is a powerful call to action for more of us to step out of the shadows and own our expertise.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://thenotboringtechwriter.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Not-Boring Tech Writer Podcast</a>
<ul>
<li>In particular, <a href="https://thenotboringtechwriter.com/episodes/the-craft-of-technical-writing-with-marcia-riefer-johnston" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The craft of technical writing with Marcia Riefer Johnston</a> talks about the snowballing power of sharing a small tidbit of information and then building on it.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://www.writethedocs.org/slack/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Write the Docs Slack</a>
<ul>
<li>Write the Docs is a global community of people who care about documentation.</li>
<li>The Slack channel contains a lot of expertise. It's been great to hear all the different voices and it is why I went to my first Write the Docs conference.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://www.writethedocs.org/conf/portland/2025/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Write the Docs, Portland (USA)</a>
<ul>
<li>A wonderful annual conference for documentarians (be they technical writers, programmers, managers, project managers, user support agents or wild enthusiasts).</li>
<li>At the conference this year (2025) I shared multiple frameworks with folks and gave a Lightning Talk. These topics will form the basis of my initial blog posts.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Over the coming weeks I'll share various tools and tricks for analysing your docs and getting insights into your users and products. I'll also share some resources for a more holistic approach to the work we do. When we think about content quality, we often focus on the docs themselves, when workplace environments and physical humans need just as much attention.</p>
<p>If you have thoughts, feedback or ideas you'd like me to expand on, you can email me at <a href="mailto:liz@lizargall.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">liz@lizargall.com</a> or create an issue in the <a href="https://github.com/lizargall/lizargall.github.io/issues" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub repository of this website</a>. If issues ever need to be moderated I'll use the <a href="https://www.writethedocs.org/conf/portland/2025/code-of-conduct/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Write the Docs Code of Conduct</a> as the framework, AKA don't be a jerk.</p>
<p>If you use any of my ideas and would like to share how they're going for you, I'd love to hear from you as well.</p>
<p>Thanks to my fellow documentarians, you make it a pleasure to write for.</p>
<p>Good things,</p>
<p>Liz</p>
<p><em><a href="mailto:liz@lizargall.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">liz@lizargall.com</a></em></p>
<p><em>11 May 2025</em></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Liz Argall</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/endiliey</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="Friends" term="Friends"/>
    </entry>
</feed>