<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Liz Argall Blog</title>
        <link>https://lizargall.github.io/blog</link>
        <description>Liz Argall Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Neurodivergent quality of life prioritization]]></title>
            <link>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/neurodivergent</link>
            <guid>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/neurodivergent</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Jump straight straight into the Neurodivergent Quality of Life Prioritization (NQLP) Matrix:]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Jump straight straight into the Neurodivergent Quality of Life Prioritization (NQLP) Matrix:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1gflZHBbMnVe6AopmU7T3MVIe2AslcvqaO8y66H27tLg/copy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Create your own copy of the NQLP</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1gflZHBbMnVe6AopmU7T3MVIe2AslcvqaO8y66H27tLg/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Master document, where you can leave comments and provide feedback</a></li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="illustration of a spiky haired character called Little Liz, a ferret is sitting on her head. Its tail is in front of of her face. A caption underneath reads &amp;quot;Dang brain weasels can make it hard to see!&amp;quot;" src="https://lizargall.github.io/assets/images/2025-05-26-neurodivergent-91295fcfddb0224e4ee7eeb26121bb38.png" width="1000" height="1294" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="creating-a-framework-to-manage-the-brain-weasels">Creating a framework to manage the brain weasels<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/neurodivergent#creating-a-framework-to-manage-the-brain-weasels" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Creating a framework to manage the brain weasels" title="Direct link to Creating a framework to manage the brain weasels">​</a></h2>
<p>Whenever life doesn't go to plan, there is an opportunity to self reflect and find opportunities to learn and grow. This is a useful habit to cultivate and can turn adversity into an alchemical experience.</p>
<p>What is not helpful, is to look at the data, look at all the variables that go into being a human and come to the conclusion that you are a trash human/need to improve across all the criteria. This is especially challenging when you're not even sure what the criteria are, or perhaps the criteria changes as you analyze yourself from different angles.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="enter-the-neurodivergent-quality-of-life-prioritization-nqlp-matrix">Enter the Neurodivergent Quality of Life Prioritization (NQLP) Matrix<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/neurodivergent#enter-the-neurodivergent-quality-of-life-prioritization-nqlp-matrix" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Enter the Neurodivergent Quality of Life Prioritization (NQLP) Matrix" title="Direct link to Enter the Neurodivergent Quality of Life Prioritization (NQLP) Matrix">​</a></h2>
<p>While the <a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/job-search">Job Search Prioritization Matrix</a> helps you think through what sorts of jobs to look for, the <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1gflZHBbMnVe6AopmU7T3MVIe2AslcvqaO8y66H27tLg/copy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">NQLP Matrix</a> helps you identify what's going well in your life and what improvements you want to prioritize. You get to choose what is important to you and self accept what's not a priority right now. You can't improve on all the criteria all the time. Maybe, for example, you need to focus on understanding when you're sleep deprived and hungry, and that in itself will help your distress tolerance around people being wrong.</p>
<p>If you choose to share your matrix with others it can be a helpful conversation starter. Sometimes people have narrow or stereotyped perceptions of what it means to be Autistic or have ADHD, through the matrix you have more opportunities to show the complexity of who you are. Maybe you're an Autistic person who's great with change, but oooh, emotional regulation when things are itchy? That might be on a totally different level.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-celebration-is-just-as-important-as-the-improvements">The celebration is just as important as the improvements<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/neurodivergent#the-celebration-is-just-as-important-as-the-improvements" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The celebration is just as important as the improvements" title="Direct link to The celebration is just as important as the improvements">​</a></h3>
<p>One of the reasons quality improvement projects can fail is because they spend too much time focusing on what needs to be improved without adequate celebration of what is going well. Don't skimp on celebrating anything that you do well.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="a-word-of-caution">A word of caution<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/neurodivergent#a-word-of-caution" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to A word of caution" title="Direct link to A word of caution">​</a></h3>
<p>This matrix could be a great tool for you to go over with a loved one or even some managers. But, a manager should never expect an employee to work on this matrix. This matrix is emotionally intimate and needs to be driven by the person filling in the matrix, not by an outside person, especially not an outside person with power.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="a-word-of-thanks-and-an-invitation">A word of thanks and an invitation<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/neurodivergent#a-word-of-thanks-and-an-invitation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to A word of thanks and an invitation" title="Direct link to A word of thanks and an invitation">​</a></h3>
<p>Thanks to the Write the Docs Portland conference for inspiring this spreadsheet. I created this while thinking about what sort of lightning talk I could do. I ended up doing a completely different lightning talk, but while I was at this conference I showed it to a lot of people. Thanks to everyone who asked questions, suggested extra criteria or laughed at the shared acknowledgements of imperfection. "Management of enthusiastic info dump over chat," anyone? This matrix has been enriched by generosity of many neurodivergent people who shared their stories and challenges. What is easy to one person can't be taken for granted by another, and this matrix helps us see ourselves and others more clearly.</p>
<p>This resource was created with neurodivergent folks in mind, if only because neurotypical people seem to be more likely to recognize when they are hungry. That said, I bet this matrix could be useful to any human. To paraphrase Rick Green, "ADHD is like height, everyone has some. It's just that if you don't realize you're 10ft tall you might think you're just really clumsy and bad with ceiling fans, when no one else has those problems. You might be so convinced you're clumsy that you never think to try out for a basketball team."</p>
<p>So, neurotypical or divergent, I encourage you to try out the spreadsheet, and I'd love to hear how it goes.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1gflZHBbMnVe6AopmU7T3MVIe2AslcvqaO8y66H27tLg/copy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Create your own copy of the NQLP</a>
<ul>
<li>This link will create your own copy</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1gflZHBbMnVe6AopmU7T3MVIe2AslcvqaO8y66H27tLg/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Master document, where you can leave comments and provide feedback</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="media-im-enjoying">Media I'm enjoying<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/neurodivergent#media-im-enjoying" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Media I'm enjoying" title="Direct link to Media I'm enjoying">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>Fabrizio Ferri Benedetti<!-- -->
<ul>
<li><a href="https://passo.uno/how-to-grow-senior-tech-writer/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">How to grow as a technical writer | Essay</a></li>
<li><a href="https://passo.uno/tips-working-tech-writers-team/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">This I remind myself when working with others | Essay</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Janine Chan, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SkpXpvTk6iU" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">7 habits of increasingly technical technical writers | Write the Docs | YouTube</a>
<ul>
<li>Come for the growth mindset, stay for the practical tips on how to be a great colleague.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Valeria Hernandez, <a href="https://valeria-writes-docs.super.site/blog/rethinking-the-user-journey-for-technical-documentation" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rethinking the user journey for technical documentation | Essay</a>
<ul>
<li>I do love a nice template!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Oliver Burkeman <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/awkwardness" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The awkwardness principle: why change rarely feels right | Essay</a></li>
<li>Ana Akana, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f49xeXdFSgc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">How to put on your face | YouTube</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="want-to-read-more-blog-posts">Want to read more blog posts?<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/neurodivergent#want-to-read-more-blog-posts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Want to read more blog posts?" title="Direct link to Want to read more blog posts?">​</a></h3>
<p><a href="https://mailchi.mp/520551e04a4d/documentarians-rock" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Subscribe to my newsletter</a> to be emailed whenever I do an update!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Templates and Spreadsheets</category>
            <category>Friends</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Job search prioritization matrix]]></title>
            <link>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/job-search</link>
            <guid>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/job-search</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Searching for work in 2025]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="searching-for-work-in-2025">Searching for work in 2025<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/job-search#searching-for-work-in-2025" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Searching for work in 2025" title="Direct link to Searching for work in 2025">​</a></h2>
<p>This blog post covers two topics:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/job-search#the-state-of-things">The state of things</a>
<ul>
<li>What it's like to be a technical writer right now and how we can carve out better spaces for ourselves.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/job-search#enter-the-prioritization-matrix">Prioritization matrix</a>
<ul>
<li>Skip straight down to this to get going with a tool that can make it easier to pursue your job search or career change dreams.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="illustration of a spiky haired character called Little Liz, she says &amp;quot;How do we get seen? And see ourselves more clearly?" src="https://lizargall.github.io/assets/images/2025-05-19-job_prioritization-73411bf513ad6b50d8e552035aa2a34d.png" width="700" height="718" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-state-of-things">The state of things<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/job-search#the-state-of-things" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The state of things" title="Direct link to The state of things">​</a></h2>
<p>It would be an understatement to say that the lives of technical writers have been destabilized by the advent of generative AI. LLMs have made it clear that many people don’t understand what we do and how much technical writers create process and maintain structures. We are more than content creators!</p>
<p>Technical writers can be powerful facilitators and diplomats, bridging gaps between teams, helping more of an organization see each other more clearly. People might see our large doc sites and think “too many words!” When what they don’t see is how our docs are much more succinct and equitably distributed than half remembered conversations that happen over and over, with less validation and more disruptions to SMEs' time.</p>
<p>Our docs are not perfect, but too often the cry of “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H6_eqxh-Qok" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">too many notes</a>!” can be a reflection of a) it is not the quantity, but the structure needs work, b) documentation is most needed when a person is new and <a href="https://ucatt.arizona.edu/news/curse-knowledge" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">the curse of knowledge</a> can make some content seem redundant or c) it can be upsetting to see your systems more clearly. We bear witness to what is and give voice to what is quietly understood, and that can be an uncomfortable thing.</p>
<p>At the recent Write the Docs conference in Portland, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4K6Bz9LM6Uc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Yanjie Niu’s talk, “The Power of Two: How Support and Documentation Teams Transform Technical Content Quality,”</a> was an inspiring example of how the roles of technical writers should evolve. It is important for us, and our employers, to see more examples like these. If you are a technical writer with similar positive experiences, I encourage you to share them, as talks or blogs. This will help us build our case and help more of us have career trajectories.</p>
<p>Short term, however, many of us are doing soul searching around what to do next. This is especially true when our superpower, writing great resumes and cover letters, gets drowned out by resumes created by generative AI. There are still opportunities for our voices to punch through, but there are volume issues to contend with.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="enter-the-prioritization-matrix">Enter the Prioritization Matrix<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/job-search#enter-the-prioritization-matrix" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Enter the Prioritization Matrix" title="Direct link to Enter the Prioritization Matrix">​</a></h2>
<p>The Prioritization Matrix, developed by <a href="https://jessicaabel.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Jessica Abel</a> as part of her Creative Focus course, has served me well when choosing what creative project to do and works for me again as I look for the next (paid) opportunity. Jessica has even used this matrix to decide what fridge to buy.</p>
<p>With Jessica’s permission, I’ve created a version of the matrix tailored towards job search activities. Using this matrix comes in about a quarter of the way through the course, so I’ve created some instructions tailored towards job search to help you get to a basic decision criteria.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://tinyurl.com/job-search-template" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://tinyurl.com/job-search-template</a>
<ul>
<li>This link will create your own copy</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://tinyurl.com/job-search-prioritization" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://tinyurl.com/job-search-prioritization</a>
<ul>
<li>This link will take you to the master document, where you can leave comments and provide feedback.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>We are impatient humans, so you may want to jump straight into playing with the template, but you’ll get even more out of it if you try out some of the instructions!</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="further-reading">Further reading<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/job-search#further-reading" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Further reading" title="Direct link to Further reading">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>Open Source, <a href="https://fanaka.readthedocs.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">“Fanaka, A handbook for African success in the international software industry.”</a>
<ul>
<li>Great advice for job seekers in any part of the world.</li>
<li><a href="https://fanaka.readthedocs.io/contribute/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Contributions are welcome</a> (and could look good on a CV)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Bob Watson, “<a href="https://docsbydesign.com/2024/03/18/a-look-at-the-past-to-see-the-future-of-technical-writing/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">A look at the past to see the future of technical writing.”</a></li>
<li>Fabrizio Ferri Benedetti, “<a href="https://passo.uno/tech-writing-predictions-2049/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Technical writing in 2049.”</a></li>
<li>Not Boring Tech Writer, <a href="https://thenotboringtechwriter.com/episodes/kate-sounds-off-on-docs-hierarchy-of-needs-and-how-we-talk-to-ourselves" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">“Kate sounds off on docs hierarchy of needs and how we talk to ourselves.”</a>
<ul>
<li>Go to nine minutes in for recognizing our superpowers and giving ourselves self-compassion.</li>
<li>We’ll need this self-compassion to be effective advocates for ourselves.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4K6Bz9LM6Uc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Yanjie Niu</a>
<ul>
<li>Write the Docs talk, “The Power of Two: How Support and Documentation Teams Transform Technical Content Quality.”</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Jessica Abel <a href="https://jessicaabel.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://jessicaabel.com/</a>
<ul>
<li>If you have a frustrated creative soul, I recommend checking out her blog, podcasts and workshops. She will give you grounded data and strategies to help you say, "Yes, I can do the thing."</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="want-to-read-more-blog-posts">Want to read more blog posts?<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/job-search#want-to-read-more-blog-posts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Want to read more blog posts?" title="Direct link to Want to read more blog posts?">​</a></h3>
<p><a href="https://mailchi.mp/520551e04a4d/documentarians-rock" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Subscribe to my newsletter</a> to be emailed whenever I do an update!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Friends</category>
            <category>Templates and Spreadsheets</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[It begins!]]></title>
            <link>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/welcome</link>
            <guid>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/welcome</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Welcome to my new technical writing blog.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to my new technical writing blog.</p>
<p>First, a big shout out to the following thought leaders who have encouraged more technical writers to share their knowledge and opinions.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://passo.uno/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Fabrizio Ferri Benedetti</a>
<ul>
<li>Terrific human whose blog posts stir conversations and help us build a better vocabulary for what we do.</li>
<li><a href="https://passo.uno/tech-writing-depth-issue/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Technical writing has a depth issue</a> is a powerful call to action for more of us to step out of the shadows and own our expertise.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://thenotboringtechwriter.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Not-Boring Tech Writer Podcast</a>
<ul>
<li>In particular, <a href="https://thenotboringtechwriter.com/episodes/the-craft-of-technical-writing-with-marcia-riefer-johnston" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The craft of technical writing with Marcia Riefer Johnston</a> talks about the snowballing power of sharing a small tidbit of information and then building on it.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://www.writethedocs.org/slack/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Write the Docs Slack</a>
<ul>
<li>Write the Docs is a global community of people who care about documentation.</li>
<li>The Slack channel contains a lot of expertise. It's been great to hear all the different voices and it is why I went to my first Write the Docs conference.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://www.writethedocs.org/conf/portland/2025/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Write the Docs, Portland (USA)</a>
<ul>
<li>A wonderful annual conference for documentarians (be they technical writers, programmers, managers, project managers, user support agents or wild enthusiasts).</li>
<li>At the conference this year (2025) I shared multiple frameworks with folks and gave a Lightning Talk. These topics will form the basis of my initial blog posts.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Over the coming weeks I'll share various tools and tricks for analysing your docs and getting insights into your users and products. I'll also share some resources for a more holistic approach to the work we do. When we think about content quality, we often focus on the docs themselves, when workplace environments and physical humans need just as much attention.</p>
<p>If you have thoughts, feedback or ideas you'd like me to expand on, you can email me at <a href="mailto:liz@lizargall.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">liz@lizargall.com</a> or create an issue in the <a href="https://github.com/lizargall/lizargall.github.io/issues" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub repository of this website</a>. If issues ever need to be moderated I'll use the <a href="https://www.writethedocs.org/conf/portland/2025/code-of-conduct/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Write the Docs Code of Conduct</a> as the framework, AKA don't be a jerk.</p>
<p>If you use any of my ideas and would like to share how they're going for you, I'd love to hear from you as well.</p>
<p>Thanks to my fellow documentarians, you make it a pleasure to write for.</p>
<p>If you'd like to get an email every time there's a blog post, <a href="https://mailchi.mp/520551e04a4d/documentarians-rock" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">subscribe to my technical writing mailing list</a>.</p>
<p>Good things,</p>
<p>Liz</p>
<p><em><a href="mailto:liz@lizargall.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">liz@lizargall.com</a></em></p>
<p><em>11 May 2025</em></p>
<p>Bonus art, we do tend to juggle a lot of things!
<img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Illustration of a pink bunny, in the style of Doctor Seuss. He&amp;#39;s balancing on a ball, wearing striped stove pipe hat. In one hand he&amp;#39;s balancing an umbrella on his paw and a goldfish bowl is balancing on the umbrella. In the other hand he is holding a book" src="https://lizargall.github.io/assets/images/2025-05-11-409-bunny-in-hat-7661e21ca3ca115e98594870a7d8a185.png" width="1440" height="1920" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Friends</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>