<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Liz Argall Blog</title>
        <link>https://lizargall.github.io/blog</link>
        <description>Liz Argall Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Management of over enthusiastic infodump over chat!]]></title>
            <link>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/infodump</link>
            <guid>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/infodump</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Infodumping is when you provide a whole lot of information all at once. It's a term that's been used for some decades when critiquing literature and has been adopted by autistic communities to refer to our tendencies to excitedly enthuse on a topic.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Infodumping" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Infodumping</a> is when you provide a whole lot of information all at once. It's a term that's been used for some decades when critiquing literature and has been adopted by autistic communities to refer to our tendencies to excitedly enthuse on a topic.</p>
<p>Documentarians (aka technical writers, content champions and word nerds) are prone to this trait. In some ways technical writing is an ongoing wrestling match with infodumping as we take on vast amounts of information, process and subject matter expertise and transform it into content that can be used and understood with greater ease.</p>
<p>In an increasingly remote world, our non-technical writing colleagues can find our facility for writing things down a little bit overwhelming. It can be especially frustrating for technical writing when even asking questions can trigger overwhelm in others as it floods their brain with new angles and questions. We can feel stuck in a bind where we're simultaneously told to ask questions, but also please don't communicate so much!</p>
<p>This is why when I was putting together the <a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/neurodivergent" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Neurodivergent Quality of Life Prioritization Matrix</a> management of over enthusiastic infodump over chat was one of the first criteria I listed.</p>
<p>In this blog post I share some tips and tricks I find helpful, as well as some advice from fellow Write the Docs peers. We'll never get it perfect, but perfect is never the point.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="thingswithout.com cartoon, Thing 1: does practice make perfect? Thing 2: no. Things 2: practice can be much more interesting. Words float in the air as the Things dance, adaptability, resilience, fluidity, new questions" src="https://lizargall.github.io/assets/images/2025-07-comic-569-perfect-4498ee3f6fe2b5e162054c1b8c83f4d5.png" width="1000" height="1294" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="its-hard-when-we-think-with-our-fingers">It's hard when we "think with our fingers!"<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/infodump#its-hard-when-we-think-with-our-fingers" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to It's hard when we &quot;think with our fingers!&quot;" title="Direct link to It's hard when we &quot;think with our fingers!&quot;">​</a></h2>
<p>I like to "think with my fingers," to have a conversation in written words. In many ways, that's what I'm doing now. This trait can sometimes get us into trouble in group chat.</p>
<p>Who else has had the following situation? Someone says (writes) something, it sparks an idea. You get excited. You reply, either in an enormous single reply wall of text, or in a series of excited smaller replies. Either way, the virtual room falls silent, and you think, "oh no, I've done it again."</p>
<p>It happens to everyone and it's a normal, natural state of things. It's how much and to what degree. To paraphrase <a href="https://www.patreon.com/c/RickGreenPatreon/posts" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rick Green</a>, infodump in chat is like height. Everyone has some, but if you're 10 feet tall you're going to have a lot more problems with ceiling fans and walking into rooms.</p>
<p>To extend the metaphor further, you might have great difficulty in normal rooms, but in the right environment you can excel. Inside at a crowded friends birthday party, you'll need to squeeze yourself down a bit, so you don't stand on people. Meanwhile, on the basketball court you might have a thrilling time as you lope around with other athletes.</p>
<p>Just grimly telling yourself, "I just need to do better," only gets you so far when you're trying to operate in multiple spaces. By the end of this blog post you should have (or be reminded of) a few more strategies, so you're not just trying to white-knuckle yourself into being smaller.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="document-workplace-operations">Document workplace operations<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/infodump#document-workplace-operations" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Document workplace operations" title="Direct link to Document workplace operations">​</a></h2>
<p>Ideally, work with your team to create or update a <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/team-playbook/plays/working-agreements" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Teams Working Agreement</a>, you'll all get a lot of benefit from the process and it's good to check in with it. If there's resistance to creating such a thing you can still document team guidelines in a formal or informal playbook.</p>
<p>It's also helpful to create a <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/blog/productivity/personal-user-manuals" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Personal User Manual</a>, and the nice thing about a Personal User Manual is that you don't need whole of team buy in to just do it for yourself. I've linked to some Atlassian tutorials for creating agreements and the manual as I like how they approach things, but these processes are completely platform agnostic.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="find-your-basketball-courts">Find your basketball courts<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/infodump#find-your-basketball-courts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Find your basketball courts" title="Direct link to Find your basketball courts">​</a></h2>
<p>Pent up energy needs go somewhere. If you have an active brain wrestling with ideas and questions, find appropriate solo and human outlets.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="journal">Journal<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/infodump#journal" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Journal" title="Direct link to Journal">​</a></h3>
<p>For real! I resisted this for a long time, especially as I had a historical tendency to spiral into negative thought patterns when I did journal. Then I realized that journalling was a great way to practice conversations with other people. I could do a lot of imaginary back and forth in my journal that historically I might have done in chat.</p>
<p>My journalling these days is predominantly to do lists, exploring ideas (such as the first draft of this blog post) and imagining conversations. It's great for processing conversations after the fact as well, I get to have my "and another thing!"... and sometimes as I explore the conversation further, without that pesky other human to annoy me, I can see their side of the story more clearly!</p>
<p>When I was a reluctant journaller I set myself the goal of 10 minutes journalling at any time of the day. These days it's often half an hour in the morning, half an hour in the evening, plus check ins and noodlings through the day. 10 minutes any time of the day is still my gold standard. I find it's important to have a really small minimum standard and feel good when I achieve it. Then it can feel like a rewarding time to settle your thoughts, rather than a big obligation.</p>
<p>I find it useful to have structured time to journal as well as having a book close to hand when I want to infodump in spaces where that's not a welcome activity. Right now I'm using <a href="https://www.officesupply.com/school-supplies/student-teacher-supplies/basic-school-supplies/notebooks/composition-book-college-graph-ruled-gray-white-sheets/p785218.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">graph/college ruled composition books</a>, so I can have stream of consciousness at the bottom and to do lists on grid paper at the top.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="colleagues-who-get-you">Colleagues who get you<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/infodump#colleagues-who-get-you" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Colleagues who get you" title="Direct link to Colleagues who get you">​</a></h3>
<p>See if there are colleagues on a similar wavelength to you that you can infodump with, either in person or over chat. It can be handy to have a regular meetup as well where you can let off steam. Establish some clear ground rules to help things flow, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Chat is asynchronous, timely replies are not an expectation</li>
<li>It's ok not to reply at all</li>
<li>Some content, cool links and so on might not be read at all.</li>
</ul>
<p>We might assume people have these implied rules, but it's still nice to make it explicit. We are process wonks after all!</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="peers-who-get-you">Peers who get you<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/infodump#peers-who-get-you" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Peers who get you" title="Direct link to Peers who get you">​</a></h3>
<p>Find other online communities where you can share some of your thoughts and explorations (while scrubbing off details where necessary). The <a href="https://www.writethedocs.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Write the Docs</a> is a good place to start with. Go for spaces that feel expansive and can help you find solutions. As a general rule, try to find spaces where you generally feel better afterwards, rather than stuck in a despairing spiral.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="organize-your-thoughts">Organize your thoughts<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/infodump#organize-your-thoughts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Organize your thoughts" title="Direct link to Organize your thoughts">​</a></h2>
<p>When in doubt draft somewhere that is not the chat, revise, then post!</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="use-meeting-agendas-to-capture-questions">Use meeting agendas to capture questions<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/infodump#use-meeting-agendas-to-capture-questions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Use meeting agendas to capture questions" title="Direct link to Use meeting agendas to capture questions">​</a></h3>
<p>I last week's article I wrote about the value of <a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/minutes">writing agendas and minutes</a>. Meeting agendas are a great place to capture questions that aren't time bound. You can use the <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1IjiFKMgSRaDVwiNBztgkKT8pPIb7hqonFmVrhSFcpzI/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">1:1 meeting template</a> I created, update the agenda in the calendar invitation, or update a task/ticket associated with the meeting</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="use-taskstickets-to-capture-thoughts">Use tasks/tickets to capture thoughts<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/infodump#use-taskstickets-to-capture-thoughts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Use tasks/tickets to capture thoughts" title="Direct link to Use tasks/tickets to capture thoughts">​</a></h3>
<p>It doesn't matter whether you use Jira, ADO, Zendesk or some in-house solution, use the project management tools in your workplace to capture your thoughts and organize them. Use tags or columns to identify how mature the idea is and how you'll circle back to them. Backlog grooming can be a handy way to sort through what's a fun distraction and what's really important.</p>
<p>A lot of people treat tasks as stubs, but you can use the comments and details section to great effect.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="create-an-enormous-document">Create an enormous document!<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/infodump#create-an-enormous-document" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Create an enormous document!" title="Direct link to Create an enormous document!">​</a></h3>
<p>When I'm onboarding to a new project or feature, I create an enormous document. I dump all my stream of consciousness into it, all my questions, all my ideas, all the requests and projects. As I get to know the team I start to refine the document. I use headers and sub-headers to group ideas.</p>
<p>I then have a great document I can go over with my leads. They can see what I'm thinking, how I'm seeing the situation. From there we can prioritize and triage the work. Solo technical writers are often thrown into the thick of things and I've found this strategy very helpful. It's basically building my own roadmap on the fly.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="work-with-a-coach">Work with a coach<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/infodump#work-with-a-coach" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Work with a coach" title="Direct link to Work with a coach">​</a></h3>
<p>Brain coaches can be as amazing or meh as a physical coach. There are ones that specialize in different types of neurodiversity and nerderies. If you don't identify as neurodiverse but despair of finding a therapist who "gets IT," try looking for a therapist who has lots of experience working with autistic adults. There are lots of autistic folks in IT, so they'll likely be more familiar with the wild worlds technical writers can inhabit.</p>
<p>Brain coaches have many different specializations and labels, and we all have slightly different goals. Diversity in goals means diversity in coaches, just like there are some folks training for an ultra-marathon, others want to train in Aikido, and some have robust knees enough to play Ultimate Frisbee! Some coaches will suit you, some won't.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="youre-not-alone">You're not alone!<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/infodump#youre-not-alone" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to You're not alone!" title="Direct link to You're not alone!">​</a></h2>
<p>I asked people in the <a href="https://www.writethedocs.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Write the Docs</a> community what strategies they had, and here's some great advice and solidarity.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="lisa-clarke"><a href="https://lisaclarke.net/hello.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lisa Clarke</a><a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/infodump#lisa-clarke" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to lisa-clarke" title="Direct link to lisa-clarke">​</a></h3>
<p>I have experienced feeling like I am spamming the group, even if everything I have to say is relevant and potentially useful. It's hard to know if a feeling like that is in your head, or if your coworkers really are thinking, "oh here she goes again with the long messages with too many details that I don't feel like reading"</p>
<p>As for how to combat that? I tend to pre-write what I want to say in a text editor, and then ruthlessly simplify it before posting. I try to embrace bullet points and eschew walls of text. I have to work to be more to-the-point in my communication, because my default mode is "super wordy".</p>
<p>In other words, I try to apply the same strategies to group messaging as I do to making my docs more readable.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="tim-mcmackin"><a href="https://timothymcmack.in/portfolio/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tim McMackin</a><a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/infodump#tim-mcmackin" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to tim-mcmackin" title="Direct link to tim-mcmackin">​</a></h3>
<p>Yeah, I've been called out on this. I'm one of the only remote employees, and we've been asked to do more discussions in private channels (as opposed to DMs) so I post a lot in slack. The only way I've been able to slow down is to spend more time doing research on my own and exhaust independent research before asking questions, even if it costs me time. I don't really like that but maybe it will build some more skills over time.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="stacey-ford">Stacey Ford<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/infodump#stacey-ford" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Stacey Ford" title="Direct link to Stacey Ford">​</a></h3>
<p>I do a lot of research before asking questions. And tend to type then pause and edit.
For work, that is. For more chatty things, like this, you see me typing things like this comment, where I add addendums and don't edit more.</p>
<p>But with work-related chat, I have found I am more successful if I research a lot then come in with a question and my thought as to what the answer might be. And I will restate things to developers when they info-dump on me.</p>
<p>I also sometimes use Jira cases as notebooks and will have a running comment going there where I info-dump and then edit before I hit save, so I can keep the notes connected to the case.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="jill-koglatis">Jill Koglatis<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/infodump#jill-koglatis" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Jill Koglatis" title="Direct link to Jill Koglatis">​</a></h3>
<p>In our team we had at different points (in different team setups) communications workshops. Those were not meant to teach any techniques, but to understand the team mates better. So cultural background, information preferences etc. Very eye-opening for everyone. It also made certain expectations clearer, for example on the extent of searching yourself before a question should be asked etc.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="media-im-enjoying">Media I'm enjoying<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/infodump#media-im-enjoying" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Media I'm enjoying" title="Direct link to Media I'm enjoying">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.atlassian.com/blog/communication/how-to-avoid-emotional-overhead-at-work" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">How to avoid “emotional overhead” at work (hint: emojis are 👍)</a></li>
<li>Cloud Native Computing Foundation (CNCF), <a href="https://github.com/cncf/mentoring/tree/main/programs/lfx-mentorship/2025/03-Sep-Nov" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sept-November Mentor/Mentee Instructions | Opportunities</a>
<ul>
<li>Project Proposals Open Wed, July 2 – Tue, July 29</li>
<li>Mentee Applications Open Wed, July 30 – Tue, August 12</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Philip Kiely, <a href="https://whopaystechnicalwriters.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Who Pays Technical Writers | Web Resource</a></li>
<li>Kapa.ai, <a href="https://docs.kapa.ai/improving/writing-best-practices" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Writing documentation for AI: best practices | Article</a></li>
<li>Abby Covert <a href="https://abbycovert.com/practicing-ia/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Practicing Information Architecture | Web Resource</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="want-to-read-more-blog-posts">Want to read more blog posts?<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/infodump#want-to-read-more-blog-posts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Want to read more blog posts?" title="Direct link to Want to read more blog posts?">​</a></h3>
<p><a href="https://mailchi.mp/520551e04a4d/documentarians-rock" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Subscribe to my newsletter</a> to be emailed whenever I do an update!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Friends</category>
            <category>Templates and Spreadsheets</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Minutes matter]]></title>
            <link>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/minutes</link>
            <guid>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/minutes</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[If you want to jump straight into the Agenda and Minutes Template:]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>If you want to jump straight into the Agenda and Minutes Template:</em></p>
<ul>
<li><em><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1IjiFKMgSRaDVwiNBztgkKT8pPIb7hqonFmVrhSFcpzI/copy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Create your own copy</a></em></li>
<li><em><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1IjiFKMgSRaDVwiNBztgkKT8pPIb7hqonFmVrhSFcpzI/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Master document, where you can leave comments and provide feedback</a></em></li>
</ul>
<p>Minutes are important, and not just how we choose to use the finite amount of time we have in life. Minutes are recordings of decisions and discussions that occurred during a meeting. Done right, they are powerful and meaningful. As a technical writer, I've often used an agenda and minutes to drive decision making, make next steps clear and to manage my own <a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/neurodivergent">enthusiastic use of workplace chat</a>!</p>
<p>I have two strong opinions (aka hot takes? but is it really hot?). One is that technical writers have a vested interested in good meeting minutes and should just start writing them if the minutes are falling short.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Comic transcript. Liz: So what did we decide? As yet unnamed character: I don&amp;#39;t know, but there sure were a lot of opinions!" src="https://lizargall.github.io/assets/images/2025-07-minutes-matter-faaf0038e62a0e8c54ca09e80d45c066.png" width="4200" height="3000" class="img_ev3q"> </p>
<p>I know some writers resist getting too close to things that might be project management, but at the end of the day we are word nerds who care about process. Where meeting minutes are not attended to it effectively it is to our benefit to make them happen and improve upon them.</p>
<p>My second strong opinion is that meeting minutes are generally poorly done, when they're done at all. Meeting minutes should be a very active part of the process, not a passive summary after the fact.</p>
<p>A transcript of who said what or who had what different opinion doesn’t matter unless it’s tied to an action item (X will investigate Y). One of the most valuable things I learned when doing non-profit governance training back in the day is that when a board makes a decision, it makes the decision. It doesn't matter if someone objected, they are bound by that decision. They may ask for something to be noted, however, that has no legal standing if your board gets sued. If a board makes a decision and you think it's unlawful, you will be held accountable to that decision unless you resign from the board! Saying, "But I said I objected! Look in the minutes!" does not protect you in any way.</p>
<p>There are times when it can be helpful to note an objection, creating a historical record, making sure something important gets heard, but it is just that. While most of us don't live with such extremes of decision making, but it is a helpful to keep in mind if you’re bogged down in who exactly said what.</p>
<p>AI has created new capabilities for transcribing meeting and creating summaries that can supplement to a well governed meeting (if company policy allows it), not stand alone. Minutes are a process as much as a record.</p>
<p>Actively take minutes during a meeting to find out what is meaningful. This will make the meetings more focused and helps to avoid circular conversations. Try:</p>
<ul>
<li>I want to get clear for the minutes, is the decision x?</li>
<li>Shall we record that we've considered y solution but have decided against it? That way we've got it documented? Do we need to stick with this for now, but set a time to re-evaluate in 6 months?</li>
<li>Shall we have an action item for Z to research the top three options and report back next meeting?</li>
<li>We've got four more items on the agenda, do we want to defer those items for later? Can we wrap up here?</li>
</ul>
<p>When emotions get high, it can be helpful to circle back to just needing to document things. You can be a neutral party, just trying to get clarity. It can be a useful way for participants to consider what it is they need to have heard, is it venting? Is it an action item? have we reached a decision but still awkwardly circling it?</p>
<p>I've created a shareable template for how I like to organize 1:1 meetings. I've found this helpful professionally as well as when working with volunteers. In my spare time I'm the co-founder of <a href="https://ngombor.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ngombor Community Development Alliance</a>. In January it was just Vince Ulargiw and me having a wild dream together and now it's a fully fledged organization. When it comes to the <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/blog/teamwork/navigate-tuckman-stages-of-team-development" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">forming, storming, norming, performing</a> stages of organizational development, we're in the forming stage and don't have formalized onboarding processes. Using this 1:1 template has been helpful as its easy to be overwhelmed by all the things we're learning, deciding and could be doing!</p>
<ul>
<li><em><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1IjiFKMgSRaDVwiNBztgkKT8pPIb7hqonFmVrhSFcpzI/copy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Create your own copy</a></em></li>
<li><em><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1IjiFKMgSRaDVwiNBztgkKT8pPIb7hqonFmVrhSFcpzI/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Master document, where you can leave comments and provide feedback</a></em></li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="media-im-enjoying">Media I'm enjoying<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/minutes#media-im-enjoying" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Media I'm enjoying" title="Direct link to Media I'm enjoying">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>Jessica Abel, <a href="https://jessicaabel.com/treat-yourself-like-a-dog/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Happiness and Productivity: You need to treat yourself like a dog | Article</a></li>
<li><a href="https://up-for-grabs.net/#/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Up For Grabs | Website</a>
<ul>
<li>Explore open source projects and jump in!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>malgamves, <a href="https://github.com/malgamves/CommunityWriterPrograms?tab=readme-ov-file" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Paid Community Writer Programs | Opportunities</a>
<ul>
<li>A great list of developer community writer programs</li>
<li>Please help them keep it up to date and add any programs you know about!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Write the Docs Australia, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_ywFBzJpGNM&amp;list=PLy70RNJ7dYrLlo1cnSh-dK5VUO8zOyB_S&amp;index=3" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Jay Stephens - Naming Guidelines, so many naming guidelines | YouTube</a>
<ul>
<li>Organisations can be very heterogeneous in their naming conventions and in their naming needs. How do we go about developing naming guidelines in these cases?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Andrew Eroh, <a href="https://andreweroh.substack.com/p/the-portfolio-problem-when-you-cant" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Portfolio Problem: When You Can’t Show Your Own Work (And AI Writers Can) | YouTube</a></li>
<li>Atlassian WorkLife, <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/blog/teamwork/navigate-tuckman-stages-of-team-development" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The agile guide to winning at team development</a></li>
<li>Tara McMullen, <a href="https://whatworks.fyi/articles/promise-rereading" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Pleasure &amp; Promise of Rereading | Article or Podcast</a>
<ul>
<li>I read it in a rush and then enjoyed re-experiencing it as a listen</li>
<li>During my second encounter I thought about how much it connects to technical writing. In this onwards grinding march of content, a good technical writer is a bastion of revisiting, revising, reworking their most important pages. Tutorials always have to be updated!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Daniele Procida, <a href="https://vurt.org/articles/my-favourite-german-word/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">My favorite German word | Article</a>
<ul>
<li>A delightful bit of thought leadership in the world of technical writing</li>
<li>After I read it I imagined what it might be like if Daniele and Tara were on a podcast together!</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="want-to-read-more-blog-posts">Want to read more blog posts?<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/minutes#want-to-read-more-blog-posts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Want to read more blog posts?" title="Direct link to Want to read more blog posts?">​</a></h3>
<p><a href="https://mailchi.mp/520551e04a4d/documentarians-rock" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Subscribe to my newsletter</a> to be emailed whenever I do an update!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Friends</category>
            <category>Templates and Spreadsheets</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Technical Writing is quite interesting!]]></title>
            <link>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/not-boring</link>
            <guid>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/not-boring</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[I had a great conversation with Kate Mueller on the Not Boring Technical Writer podcast. The actual interview was a lot longer as we got quite carried away, so kudos to the editors for squeezing it down to size.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I had a great conversation with Kate Mueller on the <a href="https://thenotboringtechwriter.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Not Boring Technical Writer</a> podcast. The actual interview was a lot longer as we got quite carried away, so kudos to the editors for squeezing it down to size.</p>
<p><a href="https://thenotboringtechwriter.com/episodes/connecting-permaculture-and-documentation-with-liz-argall" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Connecting permaculture and documentation with Liz Argall</a></p>
<p>We cover a lot of ground in the episode, including how to help engineers overcome shame that can limit documentation, the glory of the right metrics used the right way and what can happen if you throw yourself into processes passionately. You'll see connections between what we spoke about and my recent <a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/process">Attend to the Work</a> blog post.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Comic transcript. Thing 1: I just heard the best advice! Thing 2: Yeah? Thing 1: Get curious when you’re furious. Thing 2 looks a little aghast. Thing 2: YOU get furious? Thing 1 smiles. Thing 1: for sure! Thing 1: But also, curiosity makes me really really happy. Thanks to Kate Mueller for introducing me to this lovely saying." src="https://lizargall.github.io/assets/images/2025-06-26-gardener-liz-c902b1e37dfa24fa34e9ed94648a4e27.png" width="4200" height="2337" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>One of the bits that didn't make it into the episode was  Kate telling me the term "Get curious when you get furious." Wise words indeed, even when forces might want to shut your brain down. I know intimately through my Aikido practice how much more powerful I can be when I have play on my mind. We know boxers are getting ready to be dangerous when they get a little loose and light in their body. Play, joy and curiosity are not passive things!
<img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Comic transcript. Thing 1: I just heard the best advice! Thing 2: Yeah? Thing 1: Get curious when you’re furious. Thing 2 looks a little aghast. Thing 2: YOU get furious? Thing 1 smiles. Thing 1: for sure! Thing 1: But also, curiosity makes me really really happy. Thanks to Kate Mueller for introducing me to this lovely saying." src="https://lizargall.github.io/assets/images/2025-06-26-789-curious-d87df977971b8ca8a18a61ffd6cb2941.png" width="1000" height="1294" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>Right now, one of the ways I'm bringing joy and curiosity into my life is cofounding a community development organization in Uganda! You can listen to its technical writing origin story in the podcast and find out more on our website, <a href="https://ngombor.my.canva.site/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ngombor Community Development Alliance</a>.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="media-im-enjoying">Media I'm enjoying<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/not-boring#media-im-enjoying" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Media I'm enjoying" title="Direct link to Media I'm enjoying">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>Fabrizio Ferri Benedetti, <a href="https://passo.uno/things-tech-writers-shouldnt-care-about/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Things technical writers shouldn't care about... yet | Article</a>
<ul>
<li>I love this very practical guide around how to prioritize work. Great implementation of permaculture principles ;-).</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Technical Writing Uncensored (Diana Payton), <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_tKv8OhxXCY" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">He Built a Tool That Tests Your Docs — Meet Manny Silva</a></li>
<li>Refined Draft (Kevin A. Cornelius and Gabriel Laskey), <a href="https://refineddraft.substack.com/p/catch-the-failures-that-roadmaps" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Catch the Failures that Roadmaps Miss (#6)| Article</a>
<ul>
<li>Very relateable, "Even though they don’t fix the product, technical writers can identify issues before the product is released and possible impact to customers."</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Neil Patel, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VAkJXKZBtCY" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The Great Google Reset webinar | YouTube</a>
<ul>
<li>While is focused on marketers, it's super relevant for technical writers.</li>
<li>We are the masters of content that helps people learn things and tackle difficult topics. Done right that's content that really punches through in AI summaries.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Little Language Models (Delfina Hoxha), <a href="https://littlelanguagemodels.com/information-architecture-activities-formats/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">What’s the format of information architecture work: diagrams, PowerPoint, Figma, Excel? | Article</a></li>
<li>Not Boring Technical Writer (Kate Mueller):<!-- -->
<ul>
<li><a href="https://thenotboringtechwriter.com/episodes/kate-sounds-off-on-write-the-docs" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Kate sounds off on Write the Docs | Podcast</a></li>
<li><a href="https://thenotboringtechwriter.com/episodes/connecting-permaculture-and-documentation-with-liz-argall" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Connecting permaculture and documentation with Liz Argall | Podcast</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Ngazetungue Muheue, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mPP7amqTGFA&amp;t=1077s" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ubuntu Summit 2024 | Open source software between Africa and the West | YouTube</a></li>
<li><a href="https://ngombor.my.canva.site/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ngombor Community Development Alliance</a>
<ul>
<li>I'm the co-founder of an amazing non profit in Uganda. Our website just went live. If you want a little sparkle for your day go check it out.</li>
<li>We are very new, <a href="https://ngombor.my.canva.site/#sponsor-a-tree" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">please subscribe to our mailing list</a>
<ul>
<li>In addition to getting news, more subscribers can help us look stronger when applying for grants etc.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="want-to-read-more-blog-posts">Want to read more blog posts?<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/not-boring#want-to-read-more-blog-posts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Want to read more blog posts?" title="Direct link to Want to read more blog posts?">​</a></h3>
<p><a href="https://mailchi.mp/520551e04a4d/documentarians-rock" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Subscribe to my newsletter</a> to be emailed whenever I do an update!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Friends</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Attend to the work]]></title>
            <link>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/process</link>
            <guid>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/process</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[This essay started as a love letter to mindfully turning up. I wanted to write about the power that comes from turning up a little bit at a time consistently. As I attended to the work of blogging regularly it evolved to be a love letter to processes, structures, systems and their interconnections. This essay gives you a tour of philosophies and metaphors that may feel disconnected at first, but all feed into creating meaningful, effective work while avoiding burnout.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This essay started as a love letter to mindfully turning up. I wanted to write about the power that comes from turning up a little bit at a time consistently. As I attended to the work of blogging regularly it evolved to be a love letter to processes, structures, systems and their interconnections. This essay gives you a tour of philosophies and metaphors that may feel disconnected at first, but all feed into creating meaningful, effective work while avoiding burnout.</p>
<p>Due to the nature of this essay, I've only done minimal edits while typing. This essay is a love letter after all, and it wouldn't do to over work it!</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="lets-begin">Let's begin<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/process#lets-begin" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Let's begin" title="Direct link to Let's begin">​</a></h3>
<p>Over the last few blog posts, I've shared some resources for mindfully turning up for your docs and for yourself.</p>
<p>If you look at these resources you might get a sense of overwhelm. OMG, there's so much to do and I haven't done it all! It's easy for your mind to shut down and decide, if you can't do it all, what's the point?</p>
<p>All of these resources have evolved over time, through a combination of trial and error, research and reflection. And so it should go with your implementation. All of these structures are there to foster better conversations and give you different ways of focusing your attention through different helpful structures.</p>
<p>If you glance at the templates briefly, perhaps that sparks an idea or irritates you in an interesting direction. When we mindfully observe and work through patterns, templates and philosophies with a curious mind it can enrich many domains in our lives. I'm a better Aikido practitioner thanks to how deeply I care about technical writing. I am a better technical writer and colleague by thinking about how I can apply Aikido to the workplace.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-joy-of-mindful-practice">The joy of mindful practice<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/process#the-joy-of-mindful-practice" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The joy of mindful practice" title="Direct link to The joy of mindful practice">​</a></h2>
<p>In <a href="https://www.matthewsyed.co.uk/book/bounce-the-myth-of-talent-and-the-power-of-practice/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>Bounce: the Myth of Talent and the Power of Practice</em></a>, by Matthew Syed, Syed reflects on how so much of what we perceive as talent is practice that we don't see. Sometimes we don't even see our own practice, because it's "just fun" or we don't see how expertise in one domain can contribute to another.</p>
<p>In Bounce, Syed explores how it's not just any practice that helps you grow. Syed was the number one table tennis player in the UK for many years and was an Olympian twice. When he goes through his own origin story he explores how a series of happy coincidences created an environment where he was able to practice with pleasure from an early age and then have the chance to train with technical rigor at school.</p>
<p>Doing just any old practice won't make you an expert. If you practice half-heartedly doing something, 10,000 hours won't feel like expertise, it'll feel like a chore and you'll become an expert at drudging through something with diminished attention.</p>
<p>I'll never forget watching Richard Sherman, a remarkable American football player (if sadly in the news for the wrong reasons these days), warming up before a game. It was the best part of the whole day. While other people were going through the motions doing warmups to get through warmups, he was giving every motion his full attention. Every lunge, every rotation of his body, committed fully to the exercise and not bouncing out of it before completing the full stretch. His focus and ability to use this "simple" task to work with every part of his body is a memory I treasure and carry with me into my practices.</p>
<p>When Richard Sherman warmed up he aligned his consciousness with his body with his activity, filling it with intention and power. It's not just how much we practice, it's how we practice.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-pleasure-and-purpose-of-organizing-philosophies">The pleasure and purpose of organizing philosophies<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/process#the-pleasure-and-purpose-of-organizing-philosophies" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The pleasure and purpose of organizing philosophies" title="Direct link to The pleasure and purpose of organizing philosophies">​</a></h2>
<p><a href="https://sanger.umich.edu/news-1-2-19-ema-aikido/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Aikido</a> has been a love of mine since I was 19 years old, and I've been with my present dojo for about a decade. When I bow in, I try to empty my mind, splosh out all the stuff that's been building in my head. I set an intention to be present for what that practice is and to learn deeply, whether we're doing a "basic" technique or an advanced move.</p>
<p>Emptying my head helps me be present for my fellow Aikidoki as they are, not what I think they are. It helps me listen closely to newer folks, their struggles teach me so much about my craft, as new users and new minds can help me learn about my docs. Emptying my head and staying grounded in my practice helps me listen closely to the folks who have been around longer than me, my subject matter experts (SMEs). Sometimes I might be baffled about how they're trying to teach me something. If I listen closely and remain open to their teaching I can find out if they're actually trying to teach me something else. Sometimes I see how the struggles of old hands are similar to the struggles of newer folks. We can laugh at the commonalities, how we all benefit from returning to the beginning and always working on our foundations.</p>
<p>Through the constraints and structures of practice, it happens at a certain place at a certain time, our techniques have a shared vocabulary and certain people lead the experience, I have an organizational structure to actively learn in. No matter what we do at practice, I'm doing Aikido with my whole attention and that is satisfying.</p>
<p>When we mindfully turn up and know we are operating in a helpful structure, we can set aside (or turn down the volume) on a whole range of worries and perfectionisms. The question isn't, "Am I good enough?" The question becomes, "Am I doing Aikido?"</p>
<p>We can see the value of helpful structures in so many fields and amongst so many people who perform at high levels. We can see these helpful structures in the ways we build communities and interact.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="permaculture-design-principles">Permaculture design principles<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/process#permaculture-design-principles" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Permaculture design principles" title="Direct link to Permaculture design principles">​</a></h3>
<p><a href="https://permacultureprinciples.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Permaculture</a>, a philosophy and practice for sustainable land management and communities, posits the questions such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Am I listening to the ecosystem?<!-- -->
<ul>
<li>Am I trying to force my will and how "things should be" onto documents or architecture without working through what that means for that workplace and userbase?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>How can I obtain a yield?<!-- -->
<ul>
<li>Am I getting caught up in elaborate structures when I should be focused on smaller user stories?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>How do I use edges and the marginal? How am I catching and storing energy? Are we paying attention to the correct level of design?<!-- -->
<ul>
<li>Do I need to educate people that messy is ok, especially in forming and storming phases?</li>
<li>Do people feel safe contributing and that mistakes and imperfection are ok?</li>
<li>Am I getting bogged down in copy editing perfection when that time would be better served working on the big picture?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="diataxis-framework">Diataxis framework<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/process#diataxis-framework" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Diataxis framework" title="Direct link to Diataxis framework">​</a></h3>
<p>Permaculture can then blend into the <a href="https://diataxis.fr/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Diataxis framework</a>, which isn't about bludgeoning documentation into a specific shape. It's a map that helps you articulate natural rhythms that are pleasing. Diataxis can help create clarity around:</p>
<ul>
<li>The purpose of each nugget of information.</li>
<li>Developing a consistent template for readmes and features.<!-- -->
<ul>
<li>I find I apply all of Diataxis on a single page, far more than splitting things out.</li>
<li>I've found engineers find it easier to align with a template if there is a methodology behind it, it's not just me having ideas.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Trust that messy and incomplete is part of the process.<!-- -->
<ul>
<li>Permaculture is a valuable framework, but it's nice to have a call to authority that says, "Things looking bad can be a sign of improvement."</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>SMEs can find it easier to onboard people and manage the OTT infodump if you tell them their deep understanding has a place.<!-- -->
<ul>
<li>I've used Diataxis and the "teaching someone to cook" metaphor to help SMEs understand that there is a time and place for explanation, but first we need to get folks into the kitchen.</li>
<li>Saying how-to guides are like recipes has helped SMEs understand when a tutorial is required and when it's a how-to. This clear distinction has made it much easier to build trust, as programmers fear being patronizing or being patronized to. Don't worry, I wont tell you to wash your hands when it's a recipe card!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The best fertilizer is the gardener's shadow.<!-- -->
<ul>
<li>Ok, that saying is taken from gardening, but at its heart, Diataxis is just a framework for mindfully turning up for your docs and improving a bit here and there.</li>
<li>It's a continual practice, not an end point.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="open-source-principles-and-values">Open source principles and values<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/process#open-source-principles-and-values" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Open source principles and values" title="Direct link to Open source principles and values">​</a></h3>
<p>Diataxis can blend nicely into <a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/blog/open-source-culture-9-core-principles-and-values" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">open source principles</a> such as do-ocracy, collaboration and self-organization (how you turn up for your part of the garden might be really different to mine, but we both want it to thrive and a shared vocabulary helps). Open Source can invite questions such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>How are we listening to our communities?</li>
<li>How do we build environments of collaboration and respect?</li>
<li>How do we support the do-ers and make sure we're not burning through volunteers?</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="agile-methodologies">Agile methodologies<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/process#agile-methodologies" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Agile methodologies" title="Direct link to Agile methodologies">​</a></h3>
<p>Open source blends nicely into <a href="https://www.atlassian.com/agile/manifesto" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Agile methodologies</a>, where a few of the questions it asks are:</p>
<ul>
<li>How are we creating chunks of work that are purposeful?</li>
<li>How are we collaborating cross-functionally and with our customers?</li>
<li>What can we achieve now?</li>
<li>How are we valuing the energy and time of all the individuals that make up the whole?<!-- -->
<ul>
<li>As Permaculture would say, "Use and value renewable resources and services"</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="spreadsheets-and-processes-to-value-your-efforts">Spreadsheets and processes to value your efforts<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/process#spreadsheets-and-processes-to-value-your-efforts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Spreadsheets and processes to value your efforts" title="Direct link to Spreadsheets and processes to value your efforts">​</a></h2>
<p>The <a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/job-search">spreadsheets</a> I've created should have value if you glance at them. They should have greater value if you use them as a structure.</p>
<p>In Aikido, I know that if I've turned up on the mat and given my focused attention for an hour, I have done good work.</p>
<p>If I spend an hour working on a <a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/search-term-analysis">search term analysis</a>, I will have done good work. I may have improved my docs, gained a greater understanding of user experience or experienced great waves of despair as I encounter places my docs fall short. What matters on a fundamental level is that you've practiced within a supportive framework and have turned up.</p>
<p>If you don't have a structure it can be easy to think, "What have I done? I've done nothing today!" This is especially true if you encounter problems in the docs thanks to your diligence. When you don't have a container to hold and witness your work it can be easy to lose perspective.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-map-is-not-the-territory">The map is not the territory<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/process#the-map-is-not-the-territory" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The map is not the territory" title="Direct link to The map is not the territory">​</a></h2>
<p>Various helpful structures can help you see your content in new and novel ways. They can disrupt comfortable modes of seeing and get you closer to the experience of a new user. They are helpful maps, but the map is not the territory.</p>
<p>Maps can be helpful for pointing out phenomena in our shared physical universe, but they are always incomplete. They have to be, or we'd be drowned in noise. One map might be full of contour lines and show where dry riverbeds sometimes flow. Another map might crisply and cleanly focus on roads and provide the latest prices at gas stations.</p>
<p>Neither map is wrong, they just have different purposes. Sometimes, the most beautiful thing as you explore the territory is to see what seemingly disparate maps have in common. To attend to the work, to gain experience, to think deeply and see how your maps build into a larger story is satisfying.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="media-im-enjoying">Media I'm enjoying<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/process#media-im-enjoying" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Media I'm enjoying" title="Direct link to Media I'm enjoying">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>Tara McMullin<!-- -->
<ul>
<li><a href="https://whatworks.fyi/articles/validation-spiral" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Breaking The Validation Spiral: A Systems Approach | Essay or Podcast</a></li>
<li><a href="https://whatworks.fyi/articles/enabling-structures" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">How to Leverage Enabling Structures to Fulfill Values | Essay or Podcast</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Python Software Foundation (Daniele Procida), <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=710uQqIqsWk&amp;t=20s" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Python Docs Community Workshop: Introduction to Diataxis | YouTube</a>
<ul>
<li>This is a LONG video, but I like how it shows the friendly side to Diataxis that really emphasizes process over destination.</li>
<li>Tone is so much easier to convey when there are voices and faces!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Huw Richards, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YRSn-DZTGa4" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">PERMACULTURE Explained in 6 Minutes | YouTube</a></li>
<li>Aikido Journal (Josh Gold), <a href="https://aikidojournal.com/2019/11/13/aikido-a-message-and-mission-for-our-times/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Aikido: A Message and Mission for Our Time | Article</a></li>
<li>Write the Docs, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MFlGwC7DZqc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Colin Loretz - Open Docs, Open Collaboration: Building Better Documentation with Community PRs | YouTube</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="want-to-read-more-blog-posts">Want to read more blog posts?<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/process#want-to-read-more-blog-posts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Want to read more blog posts?" title="Direct link to Want to read more blog posts?">​</a></h3>
<p><a href="https://mailchi.mp/520551e04a4d/documentarians-rock" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Subscribe to my newsletter</a> to be emailed whenever I do an update!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Templates and Spreadsheets</category>
            <category>Friends</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Introduction to search term analysis]]></title>
            <link>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/search-term-analysis</link>
            <guid>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/search-term-analysis</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[If you want to jump straight into Search Term Analysis spreadsheet:]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>If you want to jump straight into Search Term Analysis spreadsheet:</em></p>
<ul>
<li><em><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1ydkOg5Zx-FUT8jYJK13C5rYNWByFvpK9Th6o5ZAK8G8/copy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Create your own copy</a></em></li>
<li><em><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1ydkOg5Zx-FUT8jYJK13C5rYNWByFvpK9Th6o5ZAK8G8" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Master document, where you can leave comments and provide feedback</a></em></li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="about">About<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/search-term-analysis#about" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to About" title="Direct link to About">​</a></h2>
<p>When we talk about <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/331088095_Beyond_Accuracy_What_Documentation_Quality_Means_to_Readers" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">content quality</a>, findability is an important factor that extends beyond clean architecture. "Can the user find the data?" is a common question. Can the user find the data if they start with a Google search takes us deeper into this investigation.</p>
<p>At the Write the Docs Conference in Portland this year I gave a lightning talk on "Google Magic!" It showed how and get insight into your documentation in five minutes. Through this approach you can get a clearer understanding of your users and identify the most impactful ways to improve your docs.</p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/gWLHKnbdkBA?si=DTtzfNL2jI2MizF9&amp;start=1058" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin"></iframe>
<p>This article goes into a bit more detail and provides a template for conducting several kinds of search term analysis.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="why-do-a-search-term-analysis">Why do a search term analysis?<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/search-term-analysis#why-do-a-search-term-analysis" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Why do a search term analysis?" title="Direct link to Why do a search term analysis?">​</a></h2>
<p>Users who actually provide feedback are a small percentage of our user base. They are often important users, they're the super users who care and will help others use our tools and services. Statistically, however, people who give feedback are outliers.</p>
<p>When you conduct a search term analysis you can think through many user personas as you come up with terms and get a suite of benefits, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>Identify content gaps and pain points</li>
<li>Prioritize content based on real-world queries</li>
<li>Interact with your content in fresh new ways helps you refresh your content</li>
<li>Make some of the invisible maintenance work you do more visible<!-- -->
<ul>
<li>It's one thing to make content improvements as general maintenance, it's another thing to make content improvements with a framework!</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<div class="theme-admonition theme-admonition-note admonition_xJq3 alert alert--secondary"><div class="admonitionHeading_Gvgb"><span class="admonitionIcon_Rf37"><svg viewBox="0 0 14 16"><path fill-rule="evenodd" d="M6.3 5.69a.942.942 0 0 1-.28-.7c0-.28.09-.52.28-.7.19-.18.42-.28.7-.28.28 0 .52.09.7.28.18.19.28.42.28.7 0 .28-.09.52-.28.7a1 1 0 0 1-.7.3c-.28 0-.52-.11-.7-.3zM8 7.99c-.02-.25-.11-.48-.31-.69-.2-.19-.42-.3-.69-.31H6c-.27.02-.48.13-.69.31-.2.2-.3.44-.31.69h1v3c.02.27.11.5.31.69.2.2.42.31.69.31h1c.27 0 .48-.11.69-.31.2-.19.3-.42.31-.69H8V7.98v.01zM7 2.3c-3.14 0-5.7 2.54-5.7 5.68 0 3.14 2.56 5.7 5.7 5.7s5.7-2.55 5.7-5.7c0-3.15-2.56-5.69-5.7-5.69v.01zM7 .98c3.86 0 7 3.14 7 7s-3.14 7-7 7-7-3.12-7-7 3.14-7 7-7z"></path></svg></span>note</div><div class="admonitionContent_BuS1"><p>There are content marketing and sales tools that can help you with some of aspects of search term analysis analysis, but they're often expensive and seldom made available to technical writers. Additionally, part of the power of this analysis is the physical process of thinking through and going through user experiences.</p></div></div>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="llm-investigation">LLM investigation<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/search-term-analysis#llm-investigation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to LLM investigation" title="Direct link to LLM investigation">​</a></h3>
<p>For this new spreadsheet, I created a tab exploring how you could analyze user experiences if they ask an LLM questions. I suggest using <a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Perplexity</a> as it is designed to provide references. It was interesting to think about how a robustly referenced Perplexity output differs from search engine output. LLMs can statistically aggregate relationships, they can provide interesting juxtapositions, but individual topics aren't explored with as much depth. LLMs provide an answer, as <a href="https://whatworks.fyi/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tara McMullin</a> would say, they prioritize efficiency and authority. LLMs will never fully replace search engines, but when used well LLMs can be a launch pad for more robustly using search engines.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="how-to-do-a-search-term-analysis">How to do a search term analysis<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/search-term-analysis#how-to-do-a-search-term-analysis" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to How to do a search term analysis" title="Direct link to How to do a search term analysis">​</a></h2>
<p>I've put the majority of the instructions in the spreadsheet, so that it can be the source of truth.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="step-1-set-up-your-spreadsheet-and-read-the-instructions">Step 1: Set up your spreadsheet and read the instructions<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/search-term-analysis#step-1-set-up-your-spreadsheet-and-read-the-instructions" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Step 1: Set up your spreadsheet and read the instructions" title="Direct link to Step 1: Set up your spreadsheet and read the instructions">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1ydkOg5Zx-FUT8jYJK13C5rYNWByFvpK9Th6o5ZAK8G8/copy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Create your own copy</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1ydkOg5Zx-FUT8jYJK13C5rYNWByFvpK9Th6o5ZAK8G8" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Master document, where you can leave comments and provide feedback</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="step-2-decide-on-your-approach">Step 2: Decide on your approach<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/search-term-analysis#step-2-decide-on-your-approach" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Step 2: Decide on your approach" title="Direct link to Step 2: Decide on your approach">​</a></h3>
<p>Once you've read through the instructions, decide on your focus. Start with the most pressing needs and potential pain points/unknowns and then iterate. While you could do this as part of a formal <a href="https://github.com/google/opendocs/blob/main/project_archetypes/audit.md" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">audit process</a>, I recommend starting it as a casual investigation. Try it out, explore the benefits and please yourself before getting too fancy!</p>
<p>I recommend starting with a quick Targeted Keyword or Google Autocomplete analysis.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="step-3-decide-when-to-share-your-findings">Step 3: Decide when to share your findings<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/search-term-analysis#step-3-decide-when-to-share-your-findings" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Step 3: Decide when to share your findings" title="Direct link to Step 3: Decide when to share your findings">​</a></h3>
<p>Unless there's a particular pain point (why can't folks find calibration information?), it's often better to chew over it, get to know your content via search term analysis over time. You may be surprised by the content improvements and insights you get exploring content in this organic, exploratory manner.</p>
<p>An analysis that fits in around other things might take a month or two. An analysis that focused on some burning questions might take a day or two!</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="step-4-reflect-on-the-process">Step 4: Reflect on the process<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/search-term-analysis#step-4-reflect-on-the-process" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Step 4: Reflect on the process" title="Direct link to Step 4: Reflect on the process">​</a></h3>
<p>What worked what didn't? Set a time for when to revisit your content, twice a year can be a helpful cadence. You may wish to schedule an analysis the month before a major announcement, so your content is prepared should there be a sudden surge in interest.</p>
<p>If you'd like to tell me how it goes, I'd love to hear about it! I'd especially love to hear about whether the LLM section is useful. Everything else in the spreadsheet is tried and tested, but that section is a new adventure. You can email me at <a href="mailto:liz@lizargall.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">liz@lizargall.com</a> or you can find me on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/lizargall/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">LinkedIn</a>.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="media-im-enjoying">Media I'm enjoying<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/search-term-analysis#media-im-enjoying" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Media I'm enjoying" title="Direct link to Media I'm enjoying">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>Technical Writer HQ, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/technical-writer-hq_i-have-no-idea-what-surface-is-supposed-to-activity-7333221367070294017-V_6S" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">A bit of fun | LinkedIn post</a></li>
<li>Google Open Source Programs Office (Elena Spitzer &amp; Erin McKean), <a href="https://opensource.googleblog.com/2025/05/introducing-new-open-source-documentation-resources.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Introducing New Open Source Documentation Resources | Announcement</a></li>
<li>Scott Abel, <a href="https://www.thecontentwrangler.com/p/content-the-unsung-hero-of-the-customer" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Content: The Unsung Hero of the Customer Experience Opera  | The Content Wrangler | Essay</a></li>
<li>Yoel Strimling, <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/331088095_Beyond_Accuracy_What_Documentation_Quality_Means_to_Readers" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Beyond Accuracy, What Documentation Quality Means to Readers | Paper</a></li>
<li>The Not Boring Tech Writer (Kate Mueller), <a href="https://thenotboringtechwriter.com/episodes/how-to-get-hired-as-a-tech-writer-with-sue-brandt" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">How to get hired as a tech writer with Sue Brandt | Podcast (with transcript)</a></li>
<li>Liz Argall, <a href="https://chatgpt.com/g/g-6841b2fc61ac8191b69ae692a522d045-daily-scheduler" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ChatGPT Daily Scheduler | Tool</a>
<ul>
<li>Write #daily and then list what you want to do.</li>
<li>The scheduler will suggest a checklist and timeline.</li>
<li>If you put too much on the list it can help you chunk up work and prioritize your day.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="want-to-read-more-blog-posts">Want to read more blog posts?<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/search-term-analysis#want-to-read-more-blog-posts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Want to read more blog posts?" title="Direct link to Want to read more blog posts?">​</a></h3>
<p><a href="https://mailchi.mp/520551e04a4d/documentarians-rock" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Subscribe to my newsletter</a> to be emailed whenever I do an update!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Templates and Spreadsheets</category>
            <category>Friends</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Neurodivergent quality of life prioritization]]></title>
            <link>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/neurodivergent</link>
            <guid>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/neurodivergent</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Jump straight straight into the Neurodivergent Quality of Life Prioritization (NQLP) Matrix:]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Jump straight straight into the Neurodivergent Quality of Life Prioritization (NQLP) Matrix:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1gflZHBbMnVe6AopmU7T3MVIe2AslcvqaO8y66H27tLg/copy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Create your own copy of the NQLP</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1gflZHBbMnVe6AopmU7T3MVIe2AslcvqaO8y66H27tLg/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Master document, where you can leave comments and provide feedback</a></li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="illustration of a spiky haired character called Little Liz, a ferret is sitting on her head. Its tail is in front of of her face. A caption underneath reads &amp;quot;Dang brain weasels can make it hard to see!&amp;quot;" src="https://lizargall.github.io/assets/images/2025-05-26-neurodivergent-91295fcfddb0224e4ee7eeb26121bb38.png" width="1000" height="1294" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="creating-a-framework-to-manage-the-brain-weasels">Creating a framework to manage the brain weasels<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/neurodivergent#creating-a-framework-to-manage-the-brain-weasels" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Creating a framework to manage the brain weasels" title="Direct link to Creating a framework to manage the brain weasels">​</a></h2>
<p>Whenever life doesn't go to plan, there is an opportunity to self reflect and find opportunities to learn and grow. This is a useful habit to cultivate and can turn adversity into an alchemical experience.</p>
<p>What is not helpful, is to look at the data, look at all the variables that go into being a human and come to the conclusion that you are a trash human/need to improve across all the criteria. This is especially challenging when you're not even sure what the criteria are, or perhaps the criteria changes as you analyze yourself from different angles.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="enter-the-neurodivergent-quality-of-life-prioritization-nqlp-matrix">Enter the Neurodivergent Quality of Life Prioritization (NQLP) Matrix<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/neurodivergent#enter-the-neurodivergent-quality-of-life-prioritization-nqlp-matrix" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Enter the Neurodivergent Quality of Life Prioritization (NQLP) Matrix" title="Direct link to Enter the Neurodivergent Quality of Life Prioritization (NQLP) Matrix">​</a></h2>
<p>While the <a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/job-search">Job Search Prioritization Matrix</a> helps you think through what sorts of jobs to look for, the <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1gflZHBbMnVe6AopmU7T3MVIe2AslcvqaO8y66H27tLg/copy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">NQLP Matrix</a> helps you identify what's going well in your life and what improvements you want to prioritize. You get to choose what is important to you and self accept what's not a priority right now. You can't improve on all the criteria all the time. Maybe, for example, you need to focus on understanding when you're sleep deprived and hungry, and that in itself will help your distress tolerance around people being wrong.</p>
<p>If you choose to share your matrix with others it can be a helpful conversation starter. Sometimes people have narrow or stereotyped perceptions of what it means to be Autistic or have ADHD, through the matrix you have more opportunities to show the complexity of who you are. Maybe you're an Autistic person who's great with change, but oooh, emotional regulation when things are itchy? That might be on a totally different level.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-celebration-is-just-as-important-as-the-improvements">The celebration is just as important as the improvements<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/neurodivergent#the-celebration-is-just-as-important-as-the-improvements" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The celebration is just as important as the improvements" title="Direct link to The celebration is just as important as the improvements">​</a></h3>
<p>One of the reasons quality improvement projects can fail is because they spend too much time focusing on what needs to be improved without adequate celebration of what is going well. Don't skimp on celebrating anything that you do well.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="a-word-of-caution">A word of caution<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/neurodivergent#a-word-of-caution" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to A word of caution" title="Direct link to A word of caution">​</a></h3>
<p>This matrix could be a great tool for you to go over with a loved one or even some managers. But, a manager should never expect an employee to work on this matrix. This matrix is emotionally intimate and needs to be driven by the person filling in the matrix, not by an outside person, especially not an outside person with power.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="a-word-of-thanks-and-an-invitation">A word of thanks and an invitation<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/neurodivergent#a-word-of-thanks-and-an-invitation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to A word of thanks and an invitation" title="Direct link to A word of thanks and an invitation">​</a></h3>
<p>Thanks to the Write the Docs Portland conference for inspiring this spreadsheet. I created this while thinking about what sort of lightning talk I could do. I ended up doing a completely different lightning talk, but while I was at this conference I showed it to a lot of people. Thanks to everyone who asked questions, suggested extra criteria or laughed at the shared acknowledgements of imperfection. "Management of enthusiastic info dump over chat," anyone? This matrix has been enriched by the generosity of many neurodivergent people who shared their stories and challenges. What is easy to one person can't be taken for granted by another, and this matrix helps us see ourselves and others more clearly.</p>
<p>This resource was created with neurodivergent folks in mind, if only because neurotypical people seem to be more likely to recognize when they are hungry. That said, I bet this matrix could be useful to any human. To paraphrase Rick Green, "ADHD is like height, everyone has some. It's just that if you don't realize you're 10ft tall you might think you're just really clumsy and bad with ceiling fans, when no one else has those problems. You might be so convinced you're clumsy that you never think to try out for a basketball team."</p>
<p>So, neurotypical or divergent, I encourage you to try out the spreadsheet, and I'd love to hear how it goes.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1gflZHBbMnVe6AopmU7T3MVIe2AslcvqaO8y66H27tLg/copy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Create your own copy of the NQLP</a>
<ul>
<li>This link will create your own copy</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1gflZHBbMnVe6AopmU7T3MVIe2AslcvqaO8y66H27tLg/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Master document, where you can leave comments and provide feedback</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="media-im-enjoying">Media I'm enjoying<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/neurodivergent#media-im-enjoying" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Media I'm enjoying" title="Direct link to Media I'm enjoying">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>Fabrizio Ferri Benedetti<!-- -->
<ul>
<li><a href="https://passo.uno/how-to-grow-senior-tech-writer/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">How to grow as a technical writer | Essay</a></li>
<li><a href="https://passo.uno/tips-working-tech-writers-team/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">This I remind myself when working with others | Essay</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Janine Chan, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SkpXpvTk6iU" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">7 habits of increasingly technical technical writers | Write the Docs | YouTube</a>
<ul>
<li>Come for the growth mindset, stay for the practical tips on how to be a great colleague.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Valeria Hernandez, <a href="https://valeria-writes-docs.super.site/blog/rethinking-the-user-journey-for-technical-documentation" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rethinking the user journey for technical documentation | Essay</a>
<ul>
<li>I do love a nice template!</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Oliver Burkeman, <a href="https://www.oliverburkeman.com/awkwardness" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The awkwardness principle: why change rarely feels right | Essay</a></li>
<li>Ana Akana, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f49xeXdFSgc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">How to put on your face | YouTube</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="want-to-read-more-blog-posts">Want to read more blog posts?<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/neurodivergent#want-to-read-more-blog-posts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Want to read more blog posts?" title="Direct link to Want to read more blog posts?">​</a></h3>
<p><a href="https://mailchi.mp/520551e04a4d/documentarians-rock" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Subscribe to my newsletter</a> to be emailed whenever I do an update!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Templates and Spreadsheets</category>
            <category>Friends</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Job search prioritization matrix]]></title>
            <link>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/job-search</link>
            <guid>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/job-search</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Searching for work in 2025]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="searching-for-work-in-2025">Searching for work in 2025<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/job-search#searching-for-work-in-2025" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Searching for work in 2025" title="Direct link to Searching for work in 2025">​</a></h2>
<p>This blog post covers two topics:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/job-search#the-state-of-things">The state of things</a>
<ul>
<li>What it's like to be a technical writer right now and how we can carve out better spaces for ourselves.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/job-search#enter-the-prioritization-matrix">Prioritization matrix</a>
<ul>
<li>Skip straight down to this to get going with a tool that can make it easier to pursue your job search or career change dreams.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="illustration of a spiky haired character called Little Liz, she says &amp;quot;How do we get seen? And see ourselves more clearly?" src="https://lizargall.github.io/assets/images/2025-05-19-job_prioritization-73411bf513ad6b50d8e552035aa2a34d.png" width="700" height="718" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-state-of-things">The state of things<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/job-search#the-state-of-things" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The state of things" title="Direct link to The state of things">​</a></h2>
<p>It would be an understatement to say that the lives of technical writers have been destabilized by the advent of generative AI. LLMs have made it clear that many people don’t understand what we do and how much technical writers create process and maintain structures. We are more than content creators!</p>
<p>Technical writers can be powerful facilitators and diplomats, bridging gaps between teams, helping more of an organization see each other more clearly. People might see our large doc sites and think “too many words!” When what they don’t see is how our docs are much more succinct and equitably distributed than half remembered conversations that happen over and over, with less validation and more disruptions to SMEs' time.</p>
<p>Our docs are not perfect, but too often the cry of “<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H6_eqxh-Qok" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">too many notes</a>!” can be a reflection of a) it is not the quantity, but the structure needs work, b) documentation is most needed when a person is new and <a href="https://ucatt.arizona.edu/news/curse-knowledge" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">the curse of knowledge</a> can make some content seem redundant or c) it can be upsetting to see your systems more clearly. We bear witness to what is and give voice to what is quietly understood, and that can be an uncomfortable thing.</p>
<p>At the recent Write the Docs conference in Portland, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4K6Bz9LM6Uc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Yanjie Niu’s talk, “The Power of Two: How Support and Documentation Teams Transform Technical Content Quality,”</a> was an inspiring example of how the roles of technical writers should evolve. It is important for us, and our employers, to see more examples like these. If you are a technical writer with similar positive experiences, I encourage you to share them, as talks or blogs. This will help us build our case and help more of us have career trajectories.</p>
<p>Short term, however, many of us are doing soul searching around what to do next. This is especially true when our superpower, writing great resumes and cover letters, gets drowned out by resumes created by generative AI. There are still opportunities for our voices to punch through, but there are volume issues to contend with.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="enter-the-prioritization-matrix">Enter the Prioritization Matrix<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/job-search#enter-the-prioritization-matrix" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Enter the Prioritization Matrix" title="Direct link to Enter the Prioritization Matrix">​</a></h2>
<p>The Prioritization Matrix, developed by <a href="https://jessicaabel.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Jessica Abel</a> as part of her Creative Focus course, has served me well when choosing what creative project to do and works for me again as I look for the next (paid) opportunity. Jessica has even used this matrix to decide what fridge to buy.</p>
<p>With Jessica’s permission, I’ve created a version of the matrix tailored towards job search activities. Using this matrix comes in about a quarter of the way through the course, so I’ve created some instructions tailored towards job search to help you get to a basic decision criteria.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://tinyurl.com/job-search-template" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://tinyurl.com/job-search-template</a>
<ul>
<li>This link will create your own copy</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://tinyurl.com/job-search-prioritization" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://tinyurl.com/job-search-prioritization</a>
<ul>
<li>This link will take you to the master document, where you can leave comments and provide feedback.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>We are impatient humans, so you may want to jump straight into playing with the template, but you’ll get even more out of it if you try out some of the instructions!</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="further-reading">Further reading<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/job-search#further-reading" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Further reading" title="Direct link to Further reading">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>Open Source, <a href="https://fanaka.readthedocs.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">“Fanaka, A handbook for African success in the international software industry.”</a>
<ul>
<li>Great advice for job seekers in any part of the world.</li>
<li><a href="https://fanaka.readthedocs.io/contribute/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Contributions are welcome</a> (and could look good on a CV)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Bob Watson, “<a href="https://docsbydesign.com/2024/03/18/a-look-at-the-past-to-see-the-future-of-technical-writing/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">A look at the past to see the future of technical writing.”</a></li>
<li>Fabrizio Ferri Benedetti, “<a href="https://passo.uno/tech-writing-predictions-2049/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Technical writing in 2049.”</a></li>
<li>Not Boring Tech Writer, <a href="https://thenotboringtechwriter.com/episodes/kate-sounds-off-on-docs-hierarchy-of-needs-and-how-we-talk-to-ourselves" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">“Kate sounds off on docs hierarchy of needs and how we talk to ourselves.”</a>
<ul>
<li>Go to nine minutes in for recognizing our superpowers and giving ourselves self-compassion.</li>
<li>We’ll need this self-compassion to be effective advocates for ourselves.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4K6Bz9LM6Uc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Yanjie Niu</a>
<ul>
<li>Write the Docs talk, “The Power of Two: How Support and Documentation Teams Transform Technical Content Quality.”</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Jessica Abel, <a href="https://jessicaabel.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://jessicaabel.com/</a>
<ul>
<li>If you have a frustrated creative soul, I recommend checking out her blog, podcasts and workshops. She will give you grounded data and strategies to help you say, "Yes, I can do the thing."</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="want-to-read-more-blog-posts">Want to read more blog posts?<a href="https://lizargall.github.io/blog/job-search#want-to-read-more-blog-posts" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Want to read more blog posts?" title="Direct link to Want to read more blog posts?">​</a></h3>
<p><a href="https://mailchi.mp/520551e04a4d/documentarians-rock" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Subscribe to my newsletter</a> to be emailed whenever I do an update!</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Friends</category>
            <category>Templates and Spreadsheets</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[It begins!]]></title>
            <link>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/welcome</link>
            <guid>https://lizargall.github.io/blog/welcome</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Welcome to my new technical writing blog.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to my new technical writing blog.</p>
<p>First, a big shout out to the following thought leaders who have encouraged more technical writers to share their knowledge and opinions.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://passo.uno/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Fabrizio Ferri Benedetti</a>
<ul>
<li>Terrific human whose blog posts stir conversations and help us build a better vocabulary for what we do.</li>
<li><a href="https://passo.uno/tech-writing-depth-issue/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Technical writing has a depth issue</a> is a powerful call to action for more of us to step out of the shadows and own our expertise.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://thenotboringtechwriter.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Not-Boring Tech Writer Podcast</a>
<ul>
<li>In particular, <a href="https://thenotboringtechwriter.com/episodes/the-craft-of-technical-writing-with-marcia-riefer-johnston" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The craft of technical writing with Marcia Riefer Johnston</a> talks about the snowballing power of sharing a small tidbit of information and then building on it.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://www.writethedocs.org/slack/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Write the Docs Slack</a>
<ul>
<li>Write the Docs is a global community of people who care about documentation.</li>
<li>The Slack channel contains a lot of expertise. It's been great to hear all the different voices and it is why I went to my first Write the Docs conference.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://www.writethedocs.org/conf/portland/2025/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Write the Docs, Portland (USA)</a>
<ul>
<li>A wonderful annual conference for documentarians (be they technical writers, programmers, managers, project managers, user support agents or wild enthusiasts).</li>
<li>At the conference this year (2025) I shared multiple frameworks with folks and gave a Lightning Talk. These topics will form the basis of my initial blog posts.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Over the coming weeks I'll share various tools and tricks for analysing your docs and getting insights into your users and products. I'll also share some resources for a more holistic approach to the work we do. When we think about content quality, we often focus on the docs themselves, when workplace environments and physical humans need just as much attention.</p>
<p>If you have thoughts, feedback or ideas you'd like me to expand on, you can email me at <a href="mailto:liz@lizargall.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">liz@lizargall.com</a> or create an issue in the <a href="https://github.com/lizargall/lizargall.github.io/issues" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub repository of this website</a>. If issues ever need to be moderated I'll use the <a href="https://www.writethedocs.org/conf/portland/2025/code-of-conduct/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Write the Docs Code of Conduct</a> as the framework, AKA don't be a jerk.</p>
<p>If you use any of my ideas and would like to share how they're going for you, I'd love to hear from you as well.</p>
<p>Thanks to my fellow documentarians, you make it a pleasure to write for.</p>
<p>If you'd like to get an email every time there's a blog post, <a href="https://mailchi.mp/520551e04a4d/documentarians-rock" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">subscribe to my technical writing mailing list</a>.</p>
<p>Good things,</p>
<p>Liz</p>
<p><em><a href="mailto:liz@lizargall.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">liz@lizargall.com</a></em></p>
<p><em>11 May 2025</em></p>
<p>Bonus art, we do tend to juggle a lot of things!
<img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Illustration of a pink bunny, in the style of Doctor Seuss. He&amp;#39;s balancing on a ball, wearing striped stove pipe hat. In one hand he&amp;#39;s balancing an umbrella on his paw and a goldfish bowl is balancing on the umbrella. In the other hand he is holding a book" src="https://lizargall.github.io/assets/images/2025-05-11-409-bunny-in-hat-7661e21ca3ca115e98594870a7d8a185.png" width="1440" height="1920" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>Friends</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>